Eleanore Pettersen Architectural Collection, 1915-2010 (bulk 1950-2000)
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
- SERIES II: Professional Papers, 1915-2002, bulk 1950-2000
  - SUBSERIES C: Awards, 1957-2002
    - (Box 78)
      - New Jersey, member Uniform Construction Code Advisory Board, 1976
      - Taliesin Fellowship, certificate, 1992
      - Sterling’s Who's Who Directory (2 folders)
    - (Box 86)
      - Cooper Union, Second Century Society, undated
      - Arts Council of Bergen County and Architects League of Northern New Jersey, Recognition certificate, 1967
      - Arts Council of Bergen County and Architects League of Northern New Jersey, County Award of Merit, 1967
      - Modern Nursing Home Administrator, Nursing Home of the Month Award for Excellence of Architectural Design, 1966
      - State of New Jersey Department of Community Affairs, certificate of appreciate for services as chairperson of the youth consultants of the New Jersey State Commission on Women, 1974
      - Sixth Annual Masonry Awards Programs, 1st place, residential multi-unit, 1989
      - New Jersey Legislature, Senate Resolution honoring and saluting Eleanore Pettersen, 1999
      - New Jersey Society of Architects, AIA, meritorious service as president, 1985
  - SUBSERIES D: Frank Lloyd Wright, 1915-2002
    Pettersen served as an apprentice to Frank Lloyd Wright as part of the Taliesin Fellowship from 1941 to 1943. Over the years, she collected material, such as newspaper and magazine clippings, newsletters (Frank Lloyd Wright Building Conservancy and FLLW Update), documenting Frank Lloyd Wright, his buildings, and his legacy. She also collected material, such as correspondence, publications, and clippings relating to Taliesin Fellows.
    - (Box 4)
      - Binder one, 1950-1959 (4 folders)
      - Binder two, 1980-1989 (4 folders)
    - (Box 5)
      - Ads for Frank Lloyd Wright homes and inspired products, 1978-1994, undated
      - Books/Exhibit catalogs
        - Book catalogs and advertisements, 1986-1995
        - Frank Lloyd Wright Home and Studio Foundation, catalogs and brochures, 1989-2001
        - J.B. Muns Fine Art Books, book catalogs, 1985-1994
        - Prairie Avenue Bookshop, book catalogs, 1992-1995
        - “Frank Lloyd Wright – Architect” exhibit at Museum of Modern Art, 1994
        - “Realizations of Usonia: Frank Lloyd Wright in Westchester,” exhibit catalog, 1985
      - Brochures and Booklets
        - Brochures, exhibits, tours, etc. regarding Frank Lloyd Wright, 1978-1997, and undated
        - “The Work of Frank Lloyd Wright in concrete Masonry,” pictorial booklet, 1989
        - “The Lighting of a Great Museum” (the Guggenheim), booklet, 1960
        - Usonian Homes, brochures, 1947
      - Calendar (based on the book “The Wright Style”), 1994
      - Clippings
        - 1949-1958 (2 folders)
        - 1960-1969
        - 1970-1979 (includes Svetlana Stalin information)
        - 1980-1989
        - 1990-1992
        - 1993-1999
        - 2000-2002
        - Undated
        - Apprentices/fellows, clippings, 1989-1993, undated
      - Correspondence about Frank Lloyd Wright and apprentices, 1981-1991
      - Encyclopedia of Frank Lloyd Wright, William Allen Storer information, 1988
      - Magazine articles (more magazine articles are located in Box 80 below)
        - 1975-1989
        - 1990-1999
        - Architectural Record, “The Wright Legacy Evaluated,” 1960
        - Harper’s, “From Bauhaus to Out House,” 1981
        - Life Houses, pages including Frank Lloyd Evaluated,” 1960
        - Northwest Architect, feature on Frank Lloyd Wright, 1969
        - Progressive Architect, “Wright Prevails,” 1987
        - Saturday Evening Post, “Frank Lloyd Wright: Defiant Genius,” 1961
        - Sergeant, John. “Frank Lloyd Wright’s Usonian Houses: the case for organic architecture,” 1975
        - WETA Magazine featuring Frank Lloyd Wright documentary, 1998
        - Wisconsin Stories, “Frank Lloyd Wright in Spring Green, 1911-1932,” 1980
      - Newsletters
        - Bulletins: The Quarterly Newsletter of the Frank Lloyd Wright Building Conservancy,” 1990-1991
        - “FLLW Update,” 1988-1996 (2 folders)
        - “Frank Lloyd Wright Newsletter,” 1981
        - “Frank Lloyd Wright Quarterly,” 1990-1992
      - Photographs/Slides (See box 11, container B below)
      - Postcards, undated
      - Taliesin
        - From letters and brochures, The Frank Lloyd Wright Foundation (Taliesin West), 1988-1997
        - “Friends of Taliesin” newsletter, 1985-1989
        - “Journal of the Taliesin Fellows,” newsletter and correspondence, 1990-1999
        - “Taliesin Fellowship News,” newsletter, 1988-1989
    - (Box 80)
      - Magazine articles
        - 1971 and undated
        - Architectural Forum, issue from January 1948
        - Architectural Forum, articles, 1949-1956
        - House + Home, articles, 1952-1955
        - Wisconsin Magazine of History, “Organic Living: Frank Lloyd Wright’s Taliesin Fellowship and Georgi Gurdjieff’s Institute for the Harmonious Development of Man,” by Robert C. Twombly, 1974-1975
        - “Wright’s Houses,” by George Nelson
    - (Box 11, Container B)
      - Buildings, 1937-1949
        - “Auldbrass Plantation,” Stevens, Yemassee, South Carolina, August 1946
        - Barnsdall (Hollyhock House), 1941
        - Dodge House – LA Gill, 1915-1916
        - Ennis, 1941-1942
        - Falling Water, 1937
        - Florida Southern, 1946
        - Guggenheim
        - Hillside, 1942
        - Jacobs House
        - Johnson Wax
        - Larkin
        - Lloyd Lewis, Riverside, IL, 1943
        - Little House, 1941
        - Marin County
        - McDowell Peak, 1942
        - Millard House, undated
        - M.I.T., July, 1949
        - Oklahoma residence, interior, 1955
        - Robie House, Chicago, IL 1909
        - Storer
        - Sturgis, 1942
        - Taliesin, 1938-1942
        - Unidentified
        - Wylie House
- SERIES III: Office Records, 1946-2003
  The Office Records series consists of materials relating to the day to day operations of a private architectural practice including financial materials, exhibit materials, publicity, clippings and scrapbooks featuring Pettersen and her practice, and photographs.
  - SUBSERIES A: General, 1962-2003
    The General subseries focuses on the daily operations of the practices with an emphasis on financial matters. Materials present include: invoices, architectural fees, budget correspondence, purchase order books (1972-2000) and appointment books (1993-1998).
    - (Box 5)
      - Architectural fees, 1994-1999, 2001 (7 folders)
      - Architectural invoices, 1982
      - Budgets (office), 1988-1989
      - Business comparison report by Dun and Bradstreet, 1994
      - CAD – Bruning Co., invoices and product information, 1985-1987
      - CAD – Holguin, contacts and product information, 1986-1987
      - Contract disputes with Picasso Painters, 1984-1985
      - Copies of employee’s pay statements, 2001
      - Correspondence, outgoing faxes, 2001 (communications to Tom, Q&A relating to legal dispute with Weissmann's’s)
      - Correspondence from Emily Schultz and Associates, 1995, 2000
      - Correspondence, fax from Emily Schultz, 2000 (regarding Cooper Union, Weissmann contract, letter and construction)
      - Credit References, 1967-1972
    - (Box 6)
      - Design Collaborative vs. Bear’s Nest, Phase I, Closing Papers, 1986, 1994
      - Estimates, 1982-1983
      - Estimating forms, undated
      - Financial records, 1981-1982
      - Interior Design Costs, 1972-1976
      - Invoices, 1981-1997
      - Invoices – consultation, 1962-1972
      - Jenson silver, letter and photos, 1992
      - Job cost record, 1961
      - Job lists, 1984 and undated (3 folders)
      - Job list/time record, 1986-1988, 1992-1994
      - Kantor, Carl, photos of sculpture and letter, 1996
      - Library, Saddle River, 2000
      - Pajoohi vs. Pettersen, 1997
      - Photographer’s bills, Alexandre Georges, 1968-1969
      - “Print book” for plan reproduction payments, 1982-2000
      - Product and architecture information file, undated
      - Professional association dues, 1974-1979
      - Prospects, 1972-1981
      - “Purchase Orders” book with project information, 1972-2000
      - Requests for proposals (from Camden Housing Authority), 1999
      - Standard details, including Nadel #5614, Troeger #5702, Gardner #5715, Lippman, and Reppen
      - State License Cards, 1989-2003
      - Weissmann vs. Pettersen, 2000
      - Unidentified poloroids and magazine clippings [associated with Stoller, Turner, Scott, and Russo?], undated
      - Unidentified sketches and product information, undated
    - (Box 88)
      - Appointment books, 1993-1998 (6 folders)
      - Reproduction of original exhibits in the Supreme Court case: The Tennessee Electric Power Company et al. v. Tennessee Valley Authority
  - SUBSERIES B: Clippings/Scrapbooks, 1957-2001
    The Clippings/Scrapbook subseries includes newspaper and magazine clippings (1957- 2000) about Pettersen and her practice, real estate ads for houses designed by Pettersen, and two scrapbooks compiled by Pettersen.
    - (Box 7)
      - Clippings
        - Pettersen, 1957-1969
        - Pettersen, 1970-1979
        - Pettersen, 1980-1989
        - Pettersen, 1990-2000
        - Pettersen, undated
        - Pettersen with correspondence, 1971-1988
        - Pettersen, houses for sale
        - AIA Bulletin featuring Pettersen, 1965
        - “At Cooper Union” publications with articles on Pettersen, 1966, 1973, 1985, 1994
        - Bear’s Nest
        - Magazine articles about Pettersen and her work, 1966-1972
        - New Jersey Society of Architects “Architecture New Jersey” publications with articles on Pettersen, 1958, 1967, 1976, 1984
        - Nixon and his house, 1981-2001
      - Scrapbooks
        - Alford-Nixon-Ushijima Residence in Saddle River, NJ (5 folders)
        - Pettersen scrapbook (2 folders)
    - (Box 80)
      - American Home, “Old Barn into Lovely Home,” May 1965
      - Star Ledger, “Meet Eleanore Pettersen, student of Frank Lloyd Wright, Designing Woman,” 2000
  - SUBSERIES C: Oversize Drawings – (rolled tubes), 1950 and undated
    - (Box 95)
      - Borough of Saddle River Master Plan, 1950
    - (Box 98)
      - Proposed Development West of Rt. 17 Saddle River, Master Plan
  - SUBSERIES D: Presentation Materials, 1991-1992
    The Presentation Materials subseries contain exhibit boards, publicity, and other materials for three exhibits featuring Pettersen.
    - (Box 6)
      - Exhibit at Arts Center of Northern New Jersey: “Eleanore Pettersen, AIA, Four Decades,” 1991
        - Invitations and Exhibit Material
        - Board and panel descriptions of projects
        - Correspondence and news clippings
        - Exhibit information (includes FAIA nomination information)
        - Photographs of exhibit
      - Exhibit at SOHO20 “Ageless Perceptions IV: Senior Women in architecture,” 1991
      - Exhibit at Pratt Manhattan Gallery, New York Center “Taliesin Legacy: The Independent Work of Frank Lloyd Wright Apprentices,” 1992
    - (Box 8, Boxes 82-83, 90-92, Map Cabinet 32 Drawer 5 Folder 1, and 2 oversize folders located on top of map cabinets 30 and 31)
      - Exhibit at Arts Center of Northern New Jersey: “Eleanore Pettersen, AIA, Four Decades,” 1991
        - Exhibit boards
    - (Box 89)
      - Exhibit panels [featuring Bear’s Nest, Mark’s residence]
      - Presentation prints
  - SUBSERIES E: Public Relations, 1954-1990
    The Public Relations series contains materials relating to the promotion of Pettersen’s practice including press clippings, correspondence between Pettersen and interviewers/media outlets, and photograph albums containing a selection of Pettersen’s projects.
    - (Box 6)
      - Alford/Nixon House, publicity clippings, 1969-1990
      - Promotion, 1954, 1967, 1973-1979
      - Publicity, 1966-1976
      - Public relations, 1969, 1972
      - Rosica, Mulhern and Associates, 1984
      - Albums
        - Anisfield residence
        - Barn (Pettersen’s home/office)
        - Bear’s Nest
        - Gardner residence
        - Glickman residence
        - Lapkin residence
        - Lenk-Benson residence
        - Marks residence
        - Segal residence
        - Seminara residence
        - Simmons residence
        - Swartley residence
        - Van Ness residence
  - SUBSERIES F: Photographs, 1946-2001
    The Photographs subseries contain glass slides, photographs, and slides of a mixture of unidentified structures and buildings designed by Pettersen. The photographs are mostly snapshots and Polaroids.
    - (Box 8)
      - Glass Slides
        - Houses – Exteriors (3 slides)
        - Houses – Interiors (3 slides)
        - Houses – Quanchi Interiors (2 slides)
        - Model – Church of St. Philip the Apostle, Clifton Lakes, NJ (13 slides)
    - (Box 9)
      - Alford/Nixon residence (#8011), 1982
      - Alford/Nixon residence
      - Anisfield, model and house, undated
      - Art Center of Northern New Jersey, #9315
      - Bear’s Nest, aerial shots by Charles L. Lutz, undated
      - Bear’s Nest, Alford/Nixon, and unidentified, undated
      - Bear’s Nest
      - Benson residence
      - Berkowitz residence #8308
      - Cabana Pools
      - Cape Cod – exterior, 1991
      - Church [?] – exterior
      - Cocozello residence
      - Contact sheets depicting Bear’s Nest, Pettersen’s home/studio, and Anisfield, undated
      - Corcoran, #9104, negatives
      - Corrodi, James, May 25, 1960
      - Dinallo #7605
      - Franklin Lakes Church, Anisfield Residence [?]
      - Gardner, 1997
      - Glickman residence
      - Hartwyck West Retirement Home
      - Henken, Patricia
      - High rise offices [?] for Saddle River
      - House, brownstone, interior and exterior
      - House, low Usonian-style, undated
      - Houses, miscellaneous
      - Houses, construction, interior and exterior
      - Houses – exteriors (2 folders)
      - Houses – exteriors – wooden house with small wrap balcony
      - Houses – exteriors – modern, pointy house by water
      - Houses – exterior – location Saddle River, NJ
      - Houses – exterior – boxy stone and wood house
      - Houses – exteriors – oriental style on hill, concrete block building, block entranceway
      - Houses – exteriors – colonial, undated
      - Houses – exterior – wooden house with wrap porch (on a hill)
      - Houses – exterior – octagon pods and swimming pool
      - Houses – interior
      - Huber residence
      - Jacobs, #9414
      - Jaeckle, construction photographs
      - Land – undeveloped
      - Lapkin [and others?] – photographs from owners showing house and landscaping project, 1985 and undated
      - Lenk and Segal residences, undated
      - Marks residence (#7402 or #7502), undated
      - Mininni, #9309
      - Model – house
      - Model – house with long breezeway and fence
      - Model – Project 143/Martha’s Vineyard, undated
      - Model – swimming pool
      - Nasson College, Westerly Campus, undated
      - Negatives – model, Pettersen’s barn, dog
      - Motel, Woodcliff Lake, NJ
      - Office building, Paramus, NJ (Lucibello)
      - Passarella, #9308
      - Pettersen’s Barn (home/studio)
      - Pettersen and her employees, 1982
      - Pettersen at her home/studio, 1973 and undated
      - Pompton Hair Salon
      - Raia, #9804
      - Rothman, 1955
      - Sadinoff residence – interior
      - Scheiber residence
      - Seminara residence
      - Structure by stone dam
      - Color transparencies – Taliesin and Taliesin West
      - Taylor #9903
      - Tennessee Valley Authority, 1951
      - Types of stone; furniture, undated
      - Viefhuse, #8402, undated
      - Weissmann, undated
    - (Box 81)
      - Pettersen’s home/studio gate, undated
      - Aerial photographs of a residence
      - Board with 12 color transparencies featuring exterior and interior of a residence
      - Church – St. Philip of the Apostle
      - Model – House with mark-ups
      - Pompton Beauty Salon – exterior
    - (Box 88)
      - Transparencies, Surfari Village, 1970
      - Unidentified house, undated
    - (Box 11, Container A)
      - Slides
        - Alford/Nixon residence, 1989 and undated
        - Barn, addition site, 1970
        - Beach, 1978 (Surfari Village?)
        - Bear’s Nest, 1987, 1990 and undated
        - Community Christian church; Pettersen’s studio; beach, March 1980
        - Coviello [#5902], 1969
        - George E. Pierce, Photographs of Pettersen residences, 1990 (includes Marks, Glickman, and unidentified)
        - Jolly House, December 1949 [Pettersen?]
        - Marks [#7402], undated
        - Nasson College construction, 1966-1967
        - Schreiber [#5603], March 1958
        - Simmons construction [#6920], 1970, 1971
        - Troeger [#5702], November 1957
        - Unidentified projects
          - Early Pettersen projects, 1946-1948 (glass slides)
          - Unidentified residence, 1958
          - Unidentified residence, 1958 [Pettersen’s barn and dog?]
          - Unidentified residences, 1968-1973 (includes several including Segal [#6506?])
          - Unidentified residence, circa 1988
          - Unidentified residence, 1988 (heavily landscaped, stone)
          - Unidentified residence featuring construction, clients, and Pettersen, 2001
        - Wilfert residence, March 1958
  - SUBSERIES G: Computer Disks, 1986-1988, and undated
    The Computer Disks subseries contains 5 ¼-inch and 3 ½-inch diskettes. They contain office records and project files. 1986-1988 and undated
    Access Restrictions
    The accessible information has been transferred to Special Collections server space, please contact Special Collections Staff for assistance in accessing this material.
- SERIES IV: Project Records, 1946-2002
  The Project Records series consists of files, specifications, drawings, and other material relating to over 650 design and construction projects carried by Pettersen with her consecutive firms Eleanore Pettersen Associates and Design Collaborative.
  Arrangement note: The Project Index is a way to organize the various formats of architectural records from the same project. The project index is organized alphabetically by client’s last name and then by project number. Researchers should note that several distinct projects share project numbers.
  - SUBSERIES A: Files, 1946-2002 (Box 14-50)
    The Files subseries consists of standard forms of agreement, change orders, invoices for architectural service, applications and certificates of payment, specifications, photographs, notes, correspondence, drawings and sketches, purchase orders, job reports, schedules, and other material created by Pettersen (and, to a certain extent, her associates) in the course of work on various residential and commercial projects. Projects primarily include the design and construction of new residences, and additions and alterations to existing residences. Most projects are located in New Jersey although there are also projects in New York, Massachusetts, Vermont, Connecticut, Maine, Michigan, Colorado, Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, Georgia, Tennessee, and Florida.
    Pettersen classified some of her files as “Dead Files.” This classification has been retained and is indicated in the Project Index with an italicized box number. The “Dead Files” include boxes 40-47.
    - See Project Index
  - SUBSERIES B: Specifications, 1956-2002 (Box 51-54)
    The Specifications subseries consist primarily of master copies, but also some draft and office copies, of specifications for various projects. Copies of specifications can also be found in the Files subseries; these copies were maintained distinct from the project files and therefore seem to warrant arrangement as a separate subseries.
    - Project Index
  - SUBSERIES C: Drawings, 1946-2002 (Box 55-75, Map-case 16,17, 28-32, Othertype 96-203)
    The Drawings subseries includes architectural plans and sketches on a variety of formats including trace paper, diazo prints, blueprints, and CAD drawings.
    - See Project Index
- SERIES V: Artifacts, and Models
  The Artifacts, Models series contains memorabilia, material samples, and models associated with Pettersen and her practice as well as Design Collaborative.
  - SUBSERIES A: Artifacts
    - (Box 79)
      - Bear’s Nest coaster
      - Leather wallet [believed to have belonged to Pettersen’s father]
      - Office stamps
        - Design Collaborative
        - Eleanore Pettersen’s signature
        - Embossing stamp, New Jersey Registered Architect
        - Embossing stamp, Design Collaborative
      - Pettersen’s nameplate
      - Tile samples (4)
      - Wooden gavel, President New Jersey Society of Architects, AIA, 1985
    - (Map-case 32 Drawer 5 Folder 8)
      - Eleanore Pettersen, FAIA business signs on corrugated plastic
  - SUBSERIES B: Architecture Models
    - (Box 204)
      - Model A
    - (Box 205)
      - Model B – Glickman Residence #8201
    - (Box 206)
      - Model C – Northern New Jersey Arts Center
    - (Box 207)
      - Model D – Yecies Associates
    - (Box 208)
      - Model E – Studio Building
      - Model F
    - (Box 209)
      - Model G
    - (Box 210)
      - Model H
    - (Box 211)
      - Model I
    - (Box 212)
      - Model J – Project 143
    - (Box 213)
      - Model K
    - (Box 214)
      - Model L
    - (Box 215)
      - Model M
    - (Box 216)
      - Model N (model in poor condition)
    - (Box 217)
      - Model O – Yecies conference table and desk
    - (Box 218)
      - Model P- (model in poor condition)
      - Model Q
      - Model R – Sadinoff #8813
- SERIES VI: Additional Donations, 1991-2003; 2010
  Records donated at a later date than the original collection and from a source other than the primary donor.
  - SUBSERIES A: Acc2010-026, 2010
    - (Box 219)
      - AIA, New Jersey Chapter, Michael Graves Lifetime Achievement Award Medal and Certificate, 2010
  - SUBSERIES B: Acc2011-076, 1991-2003
    - (Box 8)
      - Bear's Nest
      - Clippings regarding Pettersen, 1991-1995; 2003
      - Correspondence from Pettersen,1992, 1994
      - Correspondence regarding Pettersen, 1992; 2000-2001
      - Exhibit: "Eleanore Pettersen, A.I.A., Four Decades, 1991